CRAIG FRANCIS: And today we're going to
talk about ending injection vulnerabilities.
We're going to briefly cover
injection vulnerabilities, we'll talk
about how taint checking can help or
not, a special type of string,
handling some oddities, examples you
can use today and Go, Node,
JavaScript, Java, and PHP, and also
cover the future.
And what we can hopefully be able to
do in, let's say, 10 years time. The
main thing we're going to be talking
about is this quote from Mike Samuel,
which is, "Distinguishing strings
from a trusted developer, from
strings that may be attacker
controlled." By using this
distinction, we can actually stop
injection vulnerabilities from
happening. This is based on the work
from Christoph Kern, who did a talk
called Preventing Security Bugs
through Software Design. This was a
USENIX Security 2015, and AppSec
California 2016. The link is the link
to the second talk, which contains a
few extra details. It also involves
information from the book created by
some Google engineers called Building
Secure and Reliable Systems. Just
released in March 2020, and the
section if you were going to read
along is under the Common Security
Vulnerabilities chapter, starting at
page 266. Also like to give thanks to
Toby Fox for our lead actors. Undyne,
defender, and Spamton, our attacker.
Ok, so injection vulnerabilities as
we are a OS, we probably know these
bit too well. But anyway, we're going
to start with a very simple select
statement for our database, and the
developers incorrectly appended user
data onto the end. Developer expects
this to work and it kind of does work
most of the time. The problem comes
when the attacker comes in and starts
appending their own SQL onto the end
of it. So in this case, we're taking
from the user table and we're saying
where the ID is equal to minus one,
which probably won't return anything.
And then appending onto the end of
that query, we're using Union to
select additional records from the
admin table, and we probably don't
want Spamton, our attacker, to read
that information.
This is how are we supposed to do it
today with parameterized queries
where you would write the SQL as a
developer defined string, you send
that to the database. The database
parses it and creates its query
execution plan.
As a separate step, the question
marks in this case are replaced with
the user data, which is the IDs they
come in second, and that works.
Great. Another approach that we can
use is database abstractions. This is
where developers don't really want to
be writing their own SQL. Doesn't
scale. It's a bit complicated, and
the database abstractions can make
things easier.
In this case, we're going to be
looking at a very simple query, which
was looking at the articles table,
and we just see it simply saying we
want to return the articles where the
author is variable I.D. Another
approach, you know, same API, is you
would be saying, OK, where the author
ID is null and you notice there's no
user input on this one. You can also
do things like functions, function
calls. So this is not the most
efficient way of doing it because it
kind of breaks the index. But by
using the date function, you can
remove the time from the published
field and then you'll be able to
return articles that are published on
a particular date. And that's all
good.
Let's take this  a little bit
further, and we're starting off with
a query which simply returns articles
with the word count of greater than a
thousand. You could imagine this
being here for listing the articles,
which are long, you know, the long
form articles, but what defines a
long article might depend on the
person. So there may be a request to
come in to say, Well, I want to be
able to customize this. The correct
way of doing it, if you understood
the database extraction correctly,
you'd read all the documentation, you
weren't making any mistakes, is you
would provide them as two separate
values again. First of all, you would
say word count is greater than.
That's the developer to find string.
And then as a separate part, you
provide the count.
Again, nice and simple. But the sort
of mistakes that can happen can be
like this where they haven't
provided-- the developer hasn't
provided it as two separate arguments
and instead used concatenation. Now,
the database obstruction has no idea
this happened. It's just going to
accept, but because it came in as the
first argument that it can be trusted
and puts it straight into the SQL,
and this is the main problem because
the library code is usually
well-tested, well-understood and
works perfectly. But the vast
majority of problems are actually due
to the developer using the library.
It's the input to the library and
that's where we need to sort of
focus. In this case, we can give you
a quick example where Spamton has
just simply not given a count, but
has done, you know, is word count
greater than word count, which is
false. You can't have something
that's greater than itself, and then
it's doing the classic union and then
selecting additional records from the
admin table. Another example is a
database abstraction that allows you
to specify the order as just a single
argument. And this does actually come
up quite often because you often have
tables of results which are sortable
by the user, and it's so much easier
just by just simply providing the
value that is in, let's say, the URL
straight into the database
abstraction. And because ordering
doesn't necessarily refer to a single
field as in in this case, the first
name followed by the last name it
gets, it's not really properly
checked a lot of the time. So in this
case, the developer is expecting the
order by name first, followed by name
last. But Spamton can do this.
Now I'm going to give you this as a
bit of fun, really, because order by
is quite a difficult one to exploit
because after you get to the order
by part, you can't append additional
records via union, but you can do
this. You can alter the way the
sorting happens.
So in this case, we are trying to
select the number one from the admin
table when this condition passes it,
simply looking at the admin table at
record six and saying, Does the
password begin with the letter A? If
it retaining returned one, then the
order by becomes ID equals one, and
therefore the record which has an ID
of one in this case, Amy moves all
the way to the bottom of the table.
If it doesn't match, Amy stays at the
top of the table, so Spamton can
issue lots and lots of queries. So
this time now checking for password
beginning with B. Imagine that Amy
moves to the bottom and goes, Ah,
bingo, I've got the first character
of the password field and then move
on to the second character.
Obviously, we shouldn't be storing
our passwords in plain text. And if
you are interested in passwords,
there's a brilliant conference run,
typically every year on passwords.
Password Com.
That's two to three days worth of
talks on this stuff. It's really
fascinating, but I think we should
move on. Ok.
HTML.
This is the classic example. You
simply are introducing user data into
the HTML.
Spamton comes along and it simply
adds a script hack. In this case, the
evil alert.
Ideally, we'd have additional
mitigations in place, like a content
security policy to block it. But
there can be ways around that. So
what we should be doing instead is
using a library to build our HTML.
The library has understanding of the
HTML. It knows how to escape values
and understands the different context
those values can appear in. So the
HTML will typically come from a
static file or, in this case, a
string. This is more common if you're
using small snippets of HTML. You
provide that template, that string,
to the rendering, the template engine
and then you provide the user details
separately. It can then go away.
And encode those values, according to
the context. And that's great, and
that works nice and simple. And you
do have to make sure you templating
engine is context aware. Otherwise,
there are risks associated with that.
Moving on from HTML, we also have
command line injection. Again,
another simple one user data is
included directly in the command.
This fails if, because it hasn't been
escaped, so Spamton can then write
this where it's grep of a blank
string and then providing a path to
the secrets file and then the rest is
commented out. So that doesn't
actually get run. And it means that
now Spamton is effectively returning
all the lines from the secrets file.
So how do we stop mistakes?
So there's a thing called taint
checking that could help here. This
is where variables note if they are
tainted or untainted. The most
simplest version of this is you have
a string which is seen as untainted,
it gets assigned to a variable and
that in this case, the HTML variable
is now marked as untainted. If you
have a slightly longer version, it's
the different parts that make it up.
So you're starting off with an
untainted string. Your tainted
variable, in this case name, and
we're going to assume that came from
a database or a query string post
data or a cookie. And then you've got
your untainted finishing closing P
tag.
Because this HTML variable now
contains tainted data. It is also
seen as tainted, and it means that
our defending system, in this case,
the HTML templating engine can now
reject it. This is a similar example,
but we're now going to use an
escaping function. So you've got the
tainted and untainted things. We're
going to escape it to make it safe
and therefore it kind of is safe. You
know, it has been encoded correctly
for that context. Brilliant. And
therefore, HTML was seen as
untainted. But unfortunately, taint
checking incorrectly assumed escaping
makes a value safe for any context.
And that's a problem.
It creates a false sense of security.
So in this example, we have our same
setup as before. We're going to be
escaping, is this safe?
Well, no.
That didn't need to be any encoding,
but because the a href now includes
Spamton's evil alert javascript.
It means that Spamton now has a
cross-site scripting vulnerability.
Ok. How about this one? It's an image
tag. It's got a source. Sources can't
include JavaScript, so kind of safe,
so use your set up again. Is it safe?
Well, we're missing some quote marks
around the attribute and therefore it
is not safe. There was nothing in
that string that Spamton provided
which needed to be altered to be
encoded. So by providing a forward
slash, the browser returns the home
page for the image, which of course
goes wrong. And then the on error
attribute fires and then the alert is
then executed. Ok, so this is a trick
question.
We are now going to put quotes around
it. So same again, is it safe? No.
Now, I say it's a trick question,
because specifically in PHP before
8.1, which hasn't been released yet,
single quotes are not encoded by
default. Now I fortunately got that
changed beginning of this year. So if
anything breaks, please let me know.
But if anything breaks, you've
probably got a problem. But anyway.
Ok.
And another quick example with the
SQL, with my SQL in particular, with
the real escape string, because
obviously, you know, it's got to be
real. There's the tainted, untainted.
Now it's been escaped. Well, is that
safe? No. Again, we're missing quote
marks. The escape string is for
escaping the string quoting
character. Typically, the single
quotes or the double quotes. Spamton
hasn't used any of those characters,
Spamton has just simply said minus
one and then the union part is
before. So this is also vulnerable to
injection vulnerabilities. Taint
checking is close, but escaping
should be done by a third party
library, and we can simplify it by
looking for strings from a trusted
developer. We can basically shorten
it to safe versus unsafe. Safe,
specifically, when talking about
injection vulnerabilities, a string
defined by the programmer in the
source code and unsafe being
everything else. So we go back to our
examples from earlier in the prepared
query. So let's start from users
where ID equals question mark, is a
developer defined string that is said
it's safe. The ID is provided
separately and we don't care about
that. That's user data that's
supposed to be kept separate. That's
good. If we did append the user data
to the SQL, that's safe, unsafe and
therefore the SQL string itself is
now considered unsafe. And then the
database abstraction can reject this.
You can say no, not having that same
with HTML templating, safe, unsafe
values being provided.
That's good. As soon as you include
user data into it, you know we are
going to reject it. Same as before.
And likewise, with the command line
stuff. Here's just string from the
developer, the values which come in
from the user. That's good. If it's
done incorrectly, then the command
can't reject it. The same approach
can be used from the database
abstraction when the values are kept
separate. This is great. You've got
the published date is greater than
the thing. These are kept separate.
I'm just pulling this one out again
because I do need to stress the
definition of what safe is in this
context. Remember, it's safe when
talking about injection
vulnerabilities. Spamton could give
you a dodgy value or a value you
weren't expecting. Now, in a select
statement that's probably not
necessarily the worst thing this
could be a bit more important was a
delete were to do everything based on
this. So we're published is greater
than year zero. Perhaps a bit more
obvious when you're talking about rm
commands, because, you know, again,
this is technically safe from an
injection point of view. You know,
we're not really, or we can't cover
things which the developer is
allowing to happen. So this is only
safe again for injection
vulnerabilities. Spamton could set
the path to just simply saying
forward slash and then you get your
classic rm-rf joke. Obviously, a lot
of our commands now prevent this, or
at least ask you to provide an
initial argument, but there we go.
OK, so handling special cases.
This is quite a common one, which is
where you have the in clause and you
will provide it with an array of
numbers or integers, doing it this
way is very convenient.
It's quite simple. You notice I'm
just using one function, the implode.
But it's not ideal because did you
remember to ensure that they are all
integers?
When you start talking about large
projects mistakes are very easy to
make, and if you look for example at
the WordPress code base they use
where in quite a bit and there are a
few cases where they're not actually
casting it to an integer. They have
additional protections in place, so
it's not actually a vulnerability,
but we're getting into that territory
of mistakes could be made.
So, you know, in this case, we're not
converting to an integer and then we
have our where ID minus one so that
we don't get anything from the first
table and you've got your union from
the admin table again at the end. How
can we deal with this? Well, we use
parameters again, as we should be.
This time, we're just going to simply
provide the right number of question
mark parameters in there by just
simply counting up the number of IDs
that we want. That function, in
parameters count, can just be as
simple as building up and starting
off with one question mark and then
appending more as you need them. This
is perhaps the easiest to read and
understand in the context of a
program or a defined string. We could
get a little bit more fancy. And you
can build up an array of question
marks and then you can join or
implode those values together and
return that.
Same as always, you've got to be
careful with no IDs because databases
don't really like it when you say
where ID is in open bracket, closed
bracket. But you shouldn't be running
the query anyway, because it's not
going to return anything. The second
problem you might face is field names
or table names. These can't be
parameterized because they need to go
into the original SQL because the
database needs to create its query
execution plan. You can't just simply
append the value from the user, and
it's dangerous, but you could escape
the field or ensure it matches a
certain pattern. This is still risky,
but because you shouldn't really
allow them to just choose any field,
you know, you could imagine a listing
of users to a website where it's just
simply showing their name and their
profile. But if the attacker was able
to search-- sort by their email
address, the attacker can keep
changing their email address and then
sorting by the email address and
seeing where they appear on the
list. And from that, you can infer
the values from other fields in the
database, which they probably
shouldn't be able to access. How do
we deal with this? Well, we have to
have an allow list, as in only these
fields are allowed to be sorted by.
This is good practice anyway,
irrespective of this talk. So you
have your allowed list. You use the
array search function to get back the
ID of that element.
So what, you know, the order field is
defined by the user and we use what
the user said they want and we look
through that array if it matches. We
get back an ID. If it doesn't match,
we get a false-ish thing, which is
kind of zero and then we can use that
array to then pull back the
programmer defined string, so we are
simply appending on the programmer
defined string, and that means that
we are still working with the same
principle and we are also limiting to
what fields we allowed to sort by.
All good. What about config values?
So things like tables, names which
are set in INI, JSON, YAML files?
Well, we'll have to cover that in the
next section because it's going to be
down to the library to deal with it.
And the library is anyone that knows
how to deal with these safely, as in
they kind of need to be doing this
anyway. Ok, ending injection
vulnerabilities in Go.
I'd like to thank Dima for checking
over the code and Roberto for writing
up the way in which Go HTML works.
This is an example library that can
be written in Go today. First of all,
the library would create a type and
we're just going to call it string
constant. You notice it's got a
lowercase S.
So therefore it is not exported. It
also then provides a method to call
this library. And you'll notice that
it has a capital O, which means it is
exported.
Its first argument has it actually
uses its string constant and that is
required for its input.
So I put that to the side and then
the actual code from the developer.
This bit, we can kind of ignore it
basically just returning the name
from the user saying, you know,
what's their name? That's our
untrusted data. When you actually use
our method from the library, the only
accept string constant method, in
this case, we are providing it with
an untyped string. It is the
developer defined constant.
Go uses type conversion during
compilation to turn that into the
string constant. So even though it's
not exported by the package, it can
actually still be used. Next, we have
our example where the developers made
a mistake. They are using the
variable from the user. That cannot
be converted to a string constant
because it's a standard variable at
compile time still unknown, and
therefore it is rejected by the
compiler. Brilliant. That's it.
That's it sorted. So how did this
actually get used by real package in
this case? Go safe HTML or to give it
the full URL. We're going to, first
of all, look at the JavaScript part
of this. It's the simplest one to use
the script from constant method that
it provides expects the JavaScript to
be written by the developer. Now, I
personally think you shouldn't be
using in-line JavaScript, but it's
still there and this is a safe way to
doing it because the developer wrote
it. It's-- they're the one who's
trusted. If a unsafe value was
provided, something from the user and
the compiler would reject it in the
same way as shown previously.
When it comes to the HTML side of
things, with the we are kind of
having to use the query builder
pattern, but we're taking the HTML
first and it's going to be from the
template package must pass an execute
to HTML and that does the check.
The safe HTML, HTML escaped method
actually takes the value and encodes
it and returns a HTML object.
And then likewise, we see we're just
doing another thing which returns
HTML drop from developer to find
string. And then the HTML concat
function adds those three things
together and gives you the output,
which is all correctly encoded. This
approach is not content sensitive.
The templating system is, but this
kind of works. If the developer was
to make a mistake and to start using
those methods they shouldn't do by
passing in the user value like this,
compiler will reject it. And
likewise, during the concatenation
bit, if that non HTML value was
provided in, that would also be
rejected. Ok, so how we do this in
Node and one day JavaScript.
JavaScript introduced a thing called
a template literal.
This did kind of cause a bit of a
problem from the security point of
view because it made it easier to do
the wrong thing as in including a
value not being escaped.
For example, that gets included
straight away. And if that puts onto
the page, you have a problem. But
there is a new version, I say new,
still a few years old, called tagged
templates. What this does is it takes
a function and it calls it and
provides-- the JavaScript engine
provides the template in an
array-like structure. Basically, it
takes that template and splits it up
into the different component parts.
And then the values are provided
separately as additional arguments.
And here you see from the console log
output how it has broken it up and
basically what you end up having is
the first part is your developer
defined strings. And the second part
is the values. That's it being used
correctly. Unfortunately, we've seen
the case where a developer has gone,
That's a function. They call
functions with brackets. So they've
put the brackets around and then it
complains that the first argument
should be an array, so they just put
an array structure around it. And
this kind of broke the entire thing.
And what ends up happening is the
template engine would just receive
the first string and no additional
arguments, so we just went, Yeah,
that's it. Pass it straight through.
All sorted a little bit later was
also another example where that first
thing was actually provided as an
array. Likewise, but again, you'll
notice that the user value is in that
first array, not the second. So to
the rescue is a new feature called is
Template Object. Not currently
available in JavaScript, but Node
does have a poly fill. How does it
work? Well, it's just a very simple
function that you pass in the first
argument and you're simply saying, Is
this a template object, which is an
array-like structure? Ideally, you'd
also check to make sure is that sure
it is an actual array as well. But
the idea is, if this is not true,
then we throw an exception. So when
we use the tagged template correctly,
that's all good and everything's
fine. But if you don't use it
correctly now, you can throw an
exception. Nice and simple. How this
works in Node, well, first of all,
you have to install that poly fill.
Npm install is template-- template
object will just install it.
To use it, well, you just simply
require the poly first and then you
just call the function. Now I'm going
to use console dot log just to show
us through like a debug mode and
you'll notice on lines 12, 14 and 16,
that's the same three examples that I
showed you earlier. And when this
actually runs, we have basically the
first one is true because that was
used correctly, and those two other
calls which were done incorrectly get
marked as false because they are no
longer template objects. This
function is hopefully going to come
to JavaScript soon. This is the
proposal that's going through the TK
Thirty Nine process, and I'd like to
thank Christoph for working on this
at the moment. And Mike Samuel, who
we saw earlier, who started this
project off. There is a different
approach in Node, which is the Google
Closure Library. You just install it
with npm and you require it.
We're going to do our usual asking
the person for a name just so we've
got some untrustable data and then
we're using this Google dot string
dot const from method.
The idea is it's supposed to be
especially a developer defined
constant. The second one, when you're
using Node doesn't actually do
anything, it just passes it through.
It doesn't check it. But if you were
to download the closure compiler and
then use the closure compiler to make
yourself a JavaScript bundle of all
your JavaScript, then it will
actually complain. It will actually
pick up on this and go, No, that's
not good enough, and it will stop the
code from executing. Now, going back,
we're going to go off on a bit of a
tangent now. I'm going to talk about
Trusted Types. Trusted Types is
available today in JavaScript, and it
protects against DOM based cross-site
scripting vulnerabilities. And we're
going to have hopefully an extension
to this soon. As described at this
URL.
So Trusted Types as it works today,
you add it to your content security
policy and you're simply telling the
browser, We want to use Trusted Types
and we're going to use them for
script because, you know, in the
future, we might have other things
like styling. When you do your normal
JavaScript, as in, you're getting a
reference to the DOM node and using
safe methods like text content.
That's absolutely fine. That's
allowed if you use inner HTML, that's
disabled by default.
There are loads of syncs in the the
DOM API, which are less than safe.
They're quite problematic. And it's
not just in HTML, it's things like a
val, timeout, even a HREF attribute,
because obviously you can put
JavaScript into that. There are loads
of unsafe things, so the way Trusted
Types works is it basically disables
them, but it allows you a way to
check your values before they are
assigned. It's like a firewall for
protecting values. In this case, we
just create ourselves a nice, simple
object, our Trusted Type object, and
we have to provide a few different
methods, or at least one which is
named appropriately for what's going
to be useful. In this case, I'm doing
the dangerous thing of just simply
passing the values through, but
ideally you would use something like
DOM Purify to make sure you know the
value is safe. There's a new
sanitizer API that's been developed
at the moment, or you might use reg
expressions or things just to make
sure it's matching a pattern which
you know to be safe. The advantage of
this approach is it means that ninety
nine percent of your code is going to
be not using the unsafe APIs but the
times you do use it, use this method
and it means that the auditor who is
looking over your code can check it
and focus in on the problems.
To make sure your Trusted Type object
is actually understood by the browser
to be trustworthy we call a method as
in we're saying we're going to create
this policy, and here it is. The name
of it has to match a value that's in
the header as well. So we're not
making up anything that's not been
allowed.
And actually to use it is pretty much
the same as before, but you now need
to call the method to basically pass
it through that firewall-like method
that will check it and clean it and
make sure it's all OK before it goes
into the HTML again, mostly for
auditor purposes.
And this is it working correctly.
But bringing it back to the actual
core idea of this talk. All of that
code was actually quite verbose. When
you know that the string has been
written by the developer, it has no
user input and therefore it's OK. So
one of the things that's being
developed is the idea of having a
from literal method, which takes a
template that can't have any
variables in it, and it just simply
passes it through. It's a way of
simplifying it. And this is how
JavaScript is likely to get the idea
of what is a developer defined string
added to it.
And a nice, simple way in addition to
the previous bit. So Java, there is a
labor code error prone again created
by Google, and it runs extra checks
at compile time. Use your dependency
management system, and you just
append it.
All the instructions on their
website. It does have a few
dependencies, but the actual code,
the actual JavaScript or Java code,
it's quite simple. First of all, you
import the compile time constant
annotation and then you just use it
and you just simply say, but this
argument should be a compile time
constant. You get your name, the
untrusted data and then any time that
sensitive function is called, the
compiler will check that it is a
compile time constant.
If it's not, then the compiler will
reject it. There is also a Google
GWT, but I think this might be a
abandoned project because they
haven't even updated it to use https
yet. But it has a method in there
called safe HTML from Safe Constant,
which I believe works in the same
way. There is also a possibility
doing it in C++ but I never quite
worked out how to do this. The
Building Secure and Reliable Systems
Book has a single line quote of using
a template constructor that depends
on each character value in the
string, but no examples, and I'm not
entirely sure what that is. And
likewise, Google have written up a
document called Safe HTML Types
Overview, and they have a small quote
there where they talk about using
from constant. But again, there's no
real examples of how that works, so
I've not been able to get there. Ok,
so with PHP, we can use Static
Analysis.
We're going to start with Psalm. This
is the first one to implement this,
and I'd like to thank Matthew Brown
for doing this. Psalm is easily
installed with composer, has a few
dependencies.
To start your new project, you just
initialize it. And in that process,
just make sure that the error
checking level is set to three or
stricter. That's when it starts
checking the types for this
particular time. So add just simply
use, you specify that you will be
using a literal string type and for
the arguments as to how it actually
works in code, basically, the Static
Analysis tool will just pick up on
the fact that when you've actually
added in a user value into the
literal string, it will reject it.
PHP Stan is very similar, and I'd
like to thank Ondrej for this.
Composer require to install-- it just
downloads. PHP sounds slightly
different in that you have to be
level five or stricter when there's
only a single type as in your're
only accepting literal strings. But
it has to be seven or stricter when
there are multiple types. For
example, if you're accepting a
literal string or an array and in
this case, level nine is the most
strict, but it works in exactly the
same way. You just say the parameter
type is literal string. And then when
it actually picks up on the issue,
you know it rejects it from that. Ok,
so the future.
Static analysis is used by about a
third of developers, and that's good.
You know, it's good that it's
happening, but it's not really
targeting the right people. Most
developers who are probably creating
the most injection vulnerabilities
are probably not using Static
Analysis. I'd like to thank Jet
Brains for creating this survey,
which was released earlier this year,
but there is also a slight bias in
this results. It's certain developers
have filled out this form. Laravel is
a popular framework, but on the wider
system it's unlikely to be very
representative because I'm fairly
sure that WordPress does kind of take
the lead on the number of developers
in the wider world, and especially as
WordPress is not easily managed with
Static Analysis.
So this is why we can't with the PHP
and the is literal RFC.
I'd like to thank Joe and Mate on
this. Joe created the implementation.
It is available, you can add it as a
patch PHP 8.1.
And Mate did performance testing on
it to make sure that we weren't
making the process slower. This is
the website where we put the RFC.
Unfortunately, it did fail as a
through the vote, mostly because
there was some communication
problems. I wasn't very good at
explaining myself and also we
probably left it a little bit too
late to actually do the vote, as in
the vote was finishing on the last
day before feature phrase. So perhaps
quite understandably, people getting
a little bit unsure about it. Reason
I want to go about it in this
particular way, it has no
dependencies, so everyone will get it
and libraries can start using it
straight away. It is easy to use.
It's a very simple function that
allows you to just do this test.
There's no need to use Static
Analysis, but it works very well with
it. You know, so the Static Analysis
tool can actually use that function
and then sort of infer a particular
type and then work back from it. And
that would be very useful.
And this is probably the most
important is it works with existing
code and libraries. So a lot of
libraries and a lot of code already
exists, and we don't want to have to
have everyone rebuild everything with
query builders and things. You know,
this is the the argument about, you
know, do you support concatenation or
not? If you don't support
concatenation, it can help with
debugging. But if it requires you to
rewrite huge sections of code
because, you know, and it's not going
to actually improve your security by
doing so, that's a lot of work, and
therefore it probably won't help with
adoption. So we've gone with this
approach, which does support
concatenation of literal values to
aid adoption, to make it easier. And
by using a function, it allows you to
choose how to handle mistakes. So you
can write to a file, you can write to
a database, call an API, throw an
exception or just simply do nothing.
So libraries don't need everyone or--
the advantage of this approach is it
means that libraries don't need
everyone to understand and read all
of their documentation, which is kind
of the big problem because libraries
get a bit complicated. There is a lot
of methods they provide, and it's
unlikely that everyone knows exactly
what is, you know, which arguments
are safe or not. And it also doesn't
mean that we don't rely on developers
never making mistake because even the
most experienced of developers might
make a mistake and not be able to
notice it. And another thing is that
developers will be warned as soon as
they write their code. So when people
talk about security being pushed left
as in the closest to writing the code
as possible, it helps the process.
So, for example, an ID could
highlight problems as the developer
types or if they're not using an ID,
you know, this happens as soon as the
developer runs their code. So as they
are writing the code, they can find
out about the problems. Generally
speaking, we found a 0.7 percent
performance impact at a time when PHP
was getting like a 30 percent
performance improvement. We did test
this on Symfony demo without
connecting to the database. This
meant that, you know, because if we
were connected to the database,
there's too much variability. So we
were trying to find like the most
pessimistic way of measuring
performance.
How it works? Well, first of all, we
just checked to see if that function
exists with backwards compatibility
reasons. And then if it is a if it's
not a literal, then we throw an
exception. And as to how it actually
is used, we simply call the method.
And that means that every method that
the library uses, it can just call
the is literal check, which the
private method. Is this too strict?
Probably. So how about this?
Have a protection level. Zero for no
checks, one for just warnings and
make that the default and then two
for exceptions. So for those who
really want to make sure. So if
you're dealing with medical records
and banking information, you probably
want to go with exceptions, but most
people will probably be fine on
warnings. You may even have it so the
exceptions are in development mode,
but there are no checks on the
production server.
And the actual literal check that we
showed earlier, expand it a little
bit so that you do your does the
function exist or is it a literal?
That's good. Fantastic. We have a way
of sort of saying, is this an
instance of an unsafe value, which
we'll talk about in a minute. And
then you go through the different
production levels, which would either
trigger a warning or an exception. So
that special case of an unsafe value.
We have a simple stringable value
object. It shouldn't be needed. This
is how you probably use it if you
did, where you just simply say new
value-- new unsafe value and you put
your string in there, which is
unsafe, and then you can then just
call in the DB query. This is the
best example I can think of, but to
be honest, you shouldn't be doing
this. Think back to that order by
example, where we had an array of
allowed values and pulling from
there. That's probably should have
been a better approach. The other
advantage of this one is it makes it
easier for the auditors to find. So
when I'm looking through code, it'll
be really good to see, Oh yes, why
are you using that? Ok, so how about
identifiers in SQL.
It's basically the same method where
you have your query SQL and
parameters, but identifiers which is
your table names and your field
names, the things which might be
coming from the INI or the JSON or
the YAMAL config, they get provided
separately.
So you do your first check on your
SQL and then you go through the
identifiers and you just very simply
check, you know, is the identifier
acceptable? And this is very strict,
but it knows what the restrictions
are, and therefore the library is
able to safely include those
identifiers, which are no longer
literals. But they're applied after
the check, and therefore it's
perfectly safe. So then that gets
into the database.
How this looks and being used? Well,
you do DB query as the method, if
it's used correctly, where the first
argument is a developer defined
string, that's good. As soon as you
concatenate in some user data, then
it gets rejected. And this is the
example of using identifiers.
Unusual, but it's possible. And
therefore we are covering the idea of
having variable identifiers.
If you think back to that database
abstraction where we had the where
method where you could say field or
value, it meant that you can sort of
run the check on the literal check.
And likewise, with the order by. It
might have a different approach with
order by with the list of allowed
values.
Command line interface version, you
can have a parameterized exec kind of
function where we would just simply
check the base command is a literal
and we're going to throw an exception
on this one. We're going to be very
strict. This is how you'd apply the
parameters to that command. It's a
very simple loop where we just
escape  shell arg, you know, the
arguments get escaped and added to
the command and then just simply run.
This is how it would work correctly,
as in the first bit, is that
developer defined string. That's
checked. That's all good. If it's
included user data that is also
checked but rejected.
Because, yeah, same with HTML. You
can render the HTML where you have
the arguments provided that's checked
and obviously encoded correctly.
Good. If the user data included that
would be checked and rejected.
For a HTML templating engine, I was
able to create one in about three
hundred lines. You know, this is a
context aware one.
We start off with the protection
level, as we discussed earlier. I
have an array-like structure which
defines which tags are allowed, the
attributes and the the values for
those attributes. I'm using HTML
parsing with an XML mode because I
don't know, XML creates a certain
quality maybe.
More importantly, though, it ensures
that all the tags are nested
correctly and all the attributes are
quoted because you have to make sure
you're actually being quoted. There's
this little section here for walking
the nodes to find the question marks
for parameters and then the bit,
which actually does the returning of
HTML with the parameters that are now
checked. And then at the end, I've
included an unsafe value object.
Shouldn't be needed, and so far I
have not needed to use it. How this
looks. Well, a bit like the
templating engine before. I'm using
question marks for the parameters of
all the names, because in this case
we were just using short snippets and
therefore it's nice and simple. You
can also do a template and then use
it multiple times. That's good. And
if the developer makes a mistake and
includes the user data in that first
argument, it gets rejected.
Exceptions fine.
And also because it context checking
when a normal URL is included, that
is all good. If it's a JavaScript
URL, it's rejected.
And you know you can actually go a
little bit further by having a href
image source. They ensure they are
URLs. Width and height are integers
as according to the HTML spec, they
are supposed to be. Alt and
figcaption are text.
So how would this work in, let's say,
10 years time? Once all of the
libraries have started using this?
Because you notice the libraries here
are just checking their input, the
output and specifically how the
native functions like my SQL query
and my SQL prepare work. Those are
not being checked yet.
Now how we go about this is very much
up to debate. But theoretically, how
about they accept everything, but
they can warn, if not given a string
from a trusted developer? However,
there also needs to be a way for
special cases to be trusted, e.g.
strings created by a library. You'll
notice this is very similar to the
Trusted Types example we talked about
earlier in JavaScript. That
firewall-like structure. Maybe this
can be done with a stringable value
object. So that value objects we
created earlier for the unsafe value,
just rename a few things, and we'll
instead have it a way of marking this
SQL string as safe, and it still acts
like a string. But now it's sort of
wrapped in an object. How this could
be used? Well, you'd have some way to
say that this particular stringable
object is trusted.
For shortness I've just said it can
be trusted for SQL. In reality, it's
probably going to be more of a set
way of saying, Oh, it's this argument
for this method or this function,
because what is safe in one system,
they're not necessarily safe in
another. So this is probably fine for
my SQL, but might not be fine for
PostgreSQL.
When it actually comes to actually
using it, the query method in this
case will build up its SQL, which is
no longer a literal, but it will wrap
it in this DB trusted SQL value
object. But because that value object
has now been trusted, the my SQL I
query function says, Yep, that's
fine. I'm accepting that no warnings,
no errors or anything because you've
gone through that process. There
would need to be a way to disable the
check. But the beauty of this, it
means that the developers are
acknowledging the fact that they have
a problem and sort of saying, Yeah, I
know I'm doing an unsafe thing and
that's up to them. Know that's their
choice. There would need to be a way
to enforce the check because some
programs need that extra level of
protection, and it would be good for
developers who are confident their
system to be able to enforce it.
Again, talking about medical records
and banking data, anything like that.
You might want extra level.
But yeah, in short, distinguishing
strings from a trusted developer from
strings that may be attacker
controlled. With that distinction, we
can stop injection vulnerabilities.
Thank you.